We can now move to
page replacement, so this will be in two parts.
Let's start with the first one.
Let's say we end up in a situation like the
following one. We have two processes.
Each of them has an invalid entry in
the page table, so they potentially need to
load the page in
a frame, the problem is that all the frames
in the physical memory are taken, so we cannot
we don't have space to load a new one. So
here the question could be we can start thinking
about how to deal with this kind of problems:
What do we do in such a situation?
Can we replace an existing page? Can we take
one, swap it out and place the one we need?
You can imagine the answer to that is yes,
but the question would be should it be from
process one or it can also be from process
two if it's process one the one that
actually needs the page.
Can we choose the right page to swap out are there
pages that would be faster to swap out than
others?
Could it be that some page has actually very low
probability to be needed in the immediate
future? Or even in the future, or later on?
So actually swapping that out it's good because
in any case we will not need to swap it in
again and notice that this is a different
question from whether there is a page that
is faster to swap out than the other.
We could think: could we have prevented this
situation at all? Actually, so that maybe
we can do something that leads us to not ending
up in the same situation.
Maybe it's about the pages we initially allocated
to the processes and we should have given
a different number of pages to the different
processes so you see you can come
up with a lot of questions about
how to deal with this kind of situation. So
what we want to see now is that there are
basically two things we need to discuss about
all these questions. One is the frame allocation
algorithm. So how many frames you give to
each process when the process starts and the
page replacement algorithm, so which page
to replace which page to swap out,
if you end up in a situation in which you
don't have free frames, but you still need
to load the page somewhere and we start with
page replacement, so the idea is that you
want to prevent over-allocation of memory,
so we need to modify the page fault routine
because now it becomes more complex is not
just a matter of finding the page and put
it in a frame. It might also be a matter of
decide which frame should be first
emptied, taking the page that it contains and
putting it back to swap space or to the disk,
and then load the page.
As we can see, as we would see in the
future you can play tricks to optimize here.
So you could have the so called dirty bit so
an extra bit for each entry in the page table
that tells you whether the page since it was
loaded in memory was actually modified or
not, because if you did not modify the page,
then what you have there is an exact copy
of what you already have in the disk. So in
that case you don't really need to swap out,
you can just replace that page and then load
it back later on because it's the same page
you already have
in the disk.
And with this step now of adding the page
replacement algorithm inside the routine of
the page fault now we really separate the
handling of logical and physical memory. So
this sorts of completes the picture for virtual
memory.
So the basic page replacement algorithm
will look like this, so you find the location
of the desired page on this. Then you try
to find a free frame.
If there is a free frame, OK, you use it.
If there is no free frame, then you need to
use a page replacement algorithm so something
that allows you to design which should be
the victim frame. So the frame that we will
use to place the page you need and before
that to swap out the page it contains to
disk and in that case you write the victim
frame to the disk if it is dirty.
And then of course you will bring the desired
page into
the free frame and you need to update the
page table and restart with the instruction and
so on so it's the usual routine for the
page fault.
Notice that you have potentially up to two
page transfers additional page transfers.
Now with the page fault, because I may need
to swap out if you don't have or if the page
you want to swap out is actually dirty so
it has been modified since it was read from
the disk, and then you need to of course load
the page
that you need inside the frame that you have
chosen as a
victim frame
Now we're going to
look at different page replacement
algorithms
these are the four we're going to touch, but
before going into the details
this is the general picture so
when
you select which is the
victim frame, which of course depends
on the algorithm you use you need to change
to invalid the entry, you need to swap out the
victim page you need to swap in the desired
page and then you reset the page table for
the new page
but of course in the page table of the other
process, not the one that you have chosen
that contains the victim frame that you
decided to free.
we have different page
replacement algorithm because as you can
imagine, they have different tradeoffs. They
have different performance, they have different
setups in which they can be
better, let's say than others
now a question that raises here is: how do you evaluate
a page replacement algorithm? how do you see
how well it performs? You cannot really compute
such a score independently of the execution.
I mean, it depends on how the memory looks
like how many
frames you can use and what pages you have
in them and so on, so you cannot really
say how good a page replacement algorithm
is
out of context.
So the way we
do this here and at least for this course
and how we discuss these things in this lecture
is that we usually define a reference string,
so it's basically a sequence of numbers and
each number it's a page that needs to be accessed,
and then we count how many times using a specific
algorithm we need to basically choose a victim
frame. So how many times we result or the
execution results in a page fault, and the idea
is that, of course, if you are able to minimize
the number of page faults,
then that of course is a good page replacement
algorithm because
you will not pay the penalty/the extra time
for the page fault too many times how many
page faults you get will of course depend
on the algorithm you use, but I guess you
can agree with me that
in general the behavior of
the number of page faults versus the number
of frames that you have available is that
when you have a lot of frames or the more
frames you have, the less frequent should
be the
less frequent the observations of page faults
should be at the end of the day if you have
as many frames as pages in your process,
then you know that in that case that would
go to zero because it means that you can just
load the entire process and that's basically it